So pretty much everyone
gets how YouTube works
totally wrong thanks to
the insane amount of
information online that just
isn't accurate or is
confusing or is a
distraction from only the
things that matter and
there's not really that
many that do. So
in this video, I'm
gonna give you some
clarity on how YouTube
decides what to push,
the three different types
of viewers, what happens
after you post, why
good data sometimes means
nothing and how YouTube
works to grow your
business. We'll follow it
in the video after
too. And then after
this video, you'll see
a little quiz which
is gonna help you
understand if you've understood
this and if you
fail it, I'm gonna
remove you from the
course. All right, so
let's start with the
very basics of how
YouTube works. I'm only
kidding, by the way,
I'm not gonna remove
you. All right, so
what you need to
understand is that YouTube
isn't against you, but
it's also not on
your side. Really, all
it cares about is
the viewer and feeding
them more videos that
they like. If they
do that, they keep
them on the platform
for longer and that's
what makes them all
their ad revenue and
money. So to do
this, it's created something
called a viewer profile
and you are gonna
have one too. This
is where it looks
at your watch, and
then it goes, okay,
this person loves this
channel about tennis. Why
don't we push some
more videos about tennis
to them from other
channels to see what
happens there too? So
their YouTube homepage would
then have a bunch
of videos about tennis
on it and the
same down the side
of the videos that
they watch too. But
the problem we have
is this, at the
same time, it's also
gonna test a lot
of other videos from
other creators it thinks
that viewer loves too
and then it's gonna
score theirs and yours
and the one with
the highest score YouTube's
gonna keep pushing to
the viewers and more
viewers like them and
the one with the
lowest score just stops
getting pushed at all.
So this is what
makes YouTube so hard
because if your viewers
watch the biggest, most
experienced channels in your
niche that have 10
years of experience and
a giant team of
pros helping them with
a ton of data
on their side so
they know exactly what
to do to win
a viewer over, you
somehow have to get
a higher score than
them. So keep that
in mind. If you're
new to this or
small, the Faroe Islands
don't step out on
the side of the
island. They're a soccer
pitch expecting to beat
Brazil. So you need
to be very realistic
with your performance expectations.
The thing is, how
does YouTube score your
videos? Well, it does
it by looking at
data which tells it
how satisfied a viewer
was with the video
they just watched, which
is incredibly dumb because
I'm satisfied after a
tin of tomato soup.
If you wanna win
here, we need to
give our viewers their
favorite meal every time
that makes them so
flippin' fat with information
they sit there going,
oh, I'm gonna burst.
We're so good. And
there's a lot of
data YouTube looks at
to work out viewer
satisfaction. Things like, did
they watch it all
the way through, which
is known as watch
time? Did they click
it when they saw
it? And that's known
as click -through rate.
Did they hit like
or comment or share
it? The thing is,
really, all of these
distracting metrics boil down
to one question. Did
the viewer enjoy your
video enough to keep
watching YouTube? If the
answer's yes, YouTube will
show them more of
your stuff and more
people like them your
stuff too. Okay, so
that's how YouTube scores
videos so it can
work out what to
push more and then
what to drop. Let's
go a little bit
deeper now to look
at the three different
viewer types and how
they massively impact your
channel. So to start,
you need to know
this. When YouTube tests
your video with a
viewer, it's not just
testing it with one
viewer. It actually droops
different types of viewers
together into buckets and
then tests the video
with the people in
that bucket to see
how it performs with
them. If it does
well, it will push
it to more people
in the bucket who
are very similar. And
the simplest way to
look at all these
buckets is that there
are three different types.
There's fans. These are
people who watch everything
you do and have
come back on a
regular basis over the
last six months. Then
we have return viewers.
These are people who
have watched more than
one of your videos.
And then we have
cold viewers. These are
people who watch similar
content but have maybe
not discovered you yet.
So when you post
a video, YouTube starts
by testing it with
some fans. Now these
are the safest group
as they already know,
like, and trust you,
meaning they are more
likely to click. They'll
listen to everything, even
if you waffle on.
And they're going to
hit comment and like
a lot more. And
if you get high
viewer satisfaction with them,
YouTube's going to push
it to more people
in the fan bucket.
But if they don't
engage, that is a
big red flag and
YouTube's going to stop
pushing it to that
entire bucket. It also
tests it with return
viewers in the same
way. And then it
will test it with
cold viewers who are
far riskier as they
don't know, like, or
trust you yet. They
probably love your competition.
So they're really not
that interested in clicking
on your videos at
all. Meaning it's very
hard to get them
to watch and build
that viewer satisfaction. Now,
if these cold viewers
respond well, which is
statistically unlikely, YouTube's going
to aggressively push your
videos out to a
lot more of them.
And when you hit
a cold audience, the
channel goes fast, but
only three in 10
videos on world -class
creators ever do this.
So we need to
be realistic with our
expectations, which brings us
on to the most
important part, the most
understood thing on YouTube
that causes so many
people to waste hours
looking at nonsense in
their YouTube studio. So
you've been told that
you need to get
a high click for
rate on a video
so that YouTube will
push it to more
people. But if that
was true, why does
this video with millions
of views have a
lower click -through rate
than this one with
thousands? Well, what happens
to you is you're
going to post a
video and it's going
to get the best
data you've ever seen
based on all of
this stuff I just
told you, but your
views are going to
suck. And that's because
it performed well. With
the fans who inflate
your data, because they're
more likely to click
and watch for longer.
But in this case,
the cold and return
viewers, they didn't really
like it. So YouTube
just stopped pushing the
video at them. So
the data you see
only represents what the
fans for in this
situation, not the people
who grow the channel.
So it's confusing because
this data looking bad
often means more views
because it's been pushed
to so many more
cold viewers who wreck
it, but YouTube don't
care because they can
tell, that it's worth
pushing to more still,
which is just annoying,
right? And that's actually
why I ignore a
heck of a lot
of it. As you're
going to find out
in the measurement modules,
because it's mainly nonsense.
Okay, so now you
know how it scores
and serves content. Let's
look at what happens
after you post. Well,
the most likely outcome
is this. You're going
to post and a
few days later, the
views are going to
flatline and slow down,
but does that mean
it's game over? No,
not at all. I'm
going to teach you
what to do in
more details in the
launch and measurement modules.
If this happens, even
if you slow down
a bunch, YouTube continues
testing your videos across
different devices, traffic sources,
regions, viewer types, and
times a day. What
that can mean is
if your videos get
insane watch time on
TVs, but not on
mobiles, it could keep
pushing it to TVs
and completely drop you
on mobiles. Or if
your video doesn't perform
on the homepage known
as the traffic source
browse, but it does
down the side of
videos in the traffic
source known as suggested,
it will push videos
there more too. So
YouTube basically tracks where
videos are discovered known
as the traffic source,
as well as the
device they are watched
on and even locations
to see if it
should push it in
different places and slow
it down in others,
which makes this even
harder to track. Also,
another thing to realize
is that if a
newer video does get
traction, it can then
bring old videos with
it on the homepage
or suggested down the
side, as well as
in the up next
section. So just because
an old video didn't
perform doesn't mean it
might not ever. But
also sometimes the topic
of an old video
becomes relevant again, like
new cycles and trends
and seasonal events. And
what that means is
YouTube can then test
it again so it
can still get views.
And just to stop
you worrying about videos
that have views that
slow, we can still
take control of the
views ourself by pointing
end screens at them.
And you wanna know
something crazy? My channel
almost gets the same
views from end screens
as it does the
entire traffic source search.
So these are no
joke. In fact, on
Filmbooth, I generated 700
,000 views just from
people watching my end
screens. So although a
strong start when you
post a video is
what we all wanna
see, don't forget that
a video lives forever
and we can do
more to get it
lots of views. But
Ed, what if you're
new and you don't
have any fans or
return viewers yet? What
happens when you post
a video? Well, you
have to be patient
because YouTube's gonna test
your video with cold
audiences very sporadically. And
it's gonna test it
with the wrong ones
too, as it won't
really get what you're
about. So you're gonna
see views jump and
slam to a halt
and your data won't
be accurate. It's also
gonna test your video
with the wrong ones
too, as it won't
really get what you're
about. So you're gonna
see views jump and
slam to a halt
and your data won't
be accurate. It's also
gonna test your video
with the wrong ones
too, as it won't
really get what you're
about. It's also gonna
test your video with
the wrong ones too,
as it won't really
get what you're about.
with the right kind
of people, but because
you're new or small
and you need to
level up a lot
to compete on this
stage, it's very likely
you're gonna lose the
battle with your experienced
competition, pretty much most
of the time. So
if that's you, do
not quit. You are
at the hardest part
of this because you
are just not as
good or better than
your competition at making
videos yet. Now, I'm
gonna teach you how
to measure things further
down the line, but
to summarize what matters,
as you got a
heck of a lot
of info there, just
understand this, YouTube buckets
viewers into fans, return
viewers, and cold viewers.
It tests your videos
with those buckets. If
it sees high viewer
satisfaction, it pushes your
video to more people
in the bucket. If
it's low, it stops
pushing. And then sometimes
your data is gonna
look really good, but
the view's low, and
this is because it
only got pushed to
the fans. And when
your video blows up,
this data looks crap
because cold viewers wreck
data. So with all
of this being so
confusing, here's how I
look at it. Above
average views for your
channel equals good. Find
the lesson. That's the
why and repeat. Below
average views equals find
the lesson as to
why and do not
repeat. All right, so
you now understand how
YouTube works to grow
a channel. Now let's
look at how YouTube
works to grow your
business and the ways
that different viewers will
impact yourselves. So to
start, let's just bring
back this graph and
remind you of how
this works. So the
whole point of this
graph is basically 90
% of people are
just gonna quit your
topic because that's how
it works. And we
want to build a
system that stops them
quitting, but also warms
them up here in
the first 30 days
so they become a
fan and then want
to buy our stuff.
If we can build
a system that does
this, we'll get great
results. And we do
that by making tons
of videos in the
way that I show
you so that people
watch like 20 in
the first 30 days
and by getting into
our email, so we
hit them with more
value and more sales
and more simple communication
that gets them over
the line. All right,
so now let's look
at how different viewer
types are gonna impact
your business. So starting
with the cold viewers.
So when this video
blew up here, we
had a ton of
calls, but the worst
conversions of those calls
we'd ever had. And
I spoke to the
sales guys and the
team were like, Ed,
half of them didn't
even know why they
booked a call or
what this is. And
that is because often
the result of content
getting traction with a
new audience or going
viral means it brings
in much colder viewers,
but less sophisticated viewers
or idiots as you're
gonna call them. Not
only will they wreck
all your conversions, but
they'll actually sign up,
they'll do your course,
they'll instantly ask for
a refund, they'll not
turn up to your
sales calls, they'll email
you abuse, they'll complain,
this isn't what I
thought it was because
they didn't read a
single thing. And this
means if you are
hoping, this is just
a game of blowing
up videos to make
sales, it doesn't work
like that. The result
of blowing up a
video often has no
impact on your business
until a few months
later when a small
percentage of those people
have remained, gone through
the system and warmed
up enough. Okay, then
we have the fans.
These guys are a
lot nicer. They're the
red hot viewers. And
what I've found is
if you just post
consistently and try to
make videos so good,
people will like it,
they'll buy them. We
get way more of
these people coming in
and way better conversion
metrics without having to
get a huge jump
up in views. But
also because of that,
the backend of the
business is just way
easier to manage too.
I actually prefer this
slow and steady growth
because if your business
isn't infinitely scalable, this
is a much better
way to grow. So
this is where just
posting a video once
a week and not
even worrying that much
about trying to beat
your personal best comes
into play because each
video just knocks a
few more fans into
our system. The other
thing to realize about
making money on YouTube
is if you launch
a product, all of
your fans are gonna
fly in and buy
it. So your conversions
and calls and sales
spike and it all
just seems really easy.
But then a few
months later, when all
of your fans have
bought, you end up
going, why am I
not earning as much
now? And sales crash.
So this is known
as warm audience depletion.
It's very common in
organic marketing. So one
of the jobs of
our system is to
try to stop this
from happening. The thing
is, if you focus
on making your videos
so good, people can't
believe they are free,
this makes depletion far
easier to fight off.
Now, one of the
other things to note
about these types of
people is they say
things to you like,
you don't need a
sales call. I wanted
to buy straight away,
but ignore them. Red
hot fans don't realize
99 % of your
market isn't like that.
Then we have the
return viewers, they're more
casual. And for them,
we need stronger sales
and marketing to warm
up. Some will buy
easily, others won't because
they might not have
built up enough trust
yet. So with this
in mind, what we
do is we're gonna
use YouTube to make
cold viewers hot and
get hot viewers over
the line by putting
a link below every
video to your email
signup and to a
link to your sales
page too. The fans
can then hit buy
instantly and the other
two types can then
hit the email to
get more value that
warms them up and
builds trust, which then
gets them over the
line. So basically if
we boil YouTube down
to its very simplest,
all you need to
know is this, you
need to make videos
that appeal to the
cold audience so you
can grow your channel
and then follow the
steps that I'm gonna
give you to make
sure every video is
highly clickable and interesting
to them so they
come back and warm
up. Then you get
them to your email
and you make sure
they have easy access
to your product links
in those emails and
you let them know
you have an offer
too. That is all
I do to make
multiple millions every year.
But the secret to
all of this is
the free YouTube content.
So do the quiz
next and then move
on to the next
video where I'm gonna
show you how to
build a channel that
brings people back and
grows a business via
something called positioning. So
that's how YouTube works.
Go and do the
quiz to make sure
you understand that and
then move on to
the next video. I'm
gonna show you how
YouTube works to generate
you more sales and
emails. And don't skip
the quiz. I can
see what you're doing
in my analytics by
the way. And I
do spy on you.